The universe
الكون
is really big.
كبير جداُ.
We live in a galaxy, the Milky Way Galaxy.
نحن نعيش في مجرة، مجرة درب التبانة.
There are about a hundred billion stars in the Milky Way Galaxy.
يوجد نحو مائة بليون نجمة في مجرة درب التبانة.
And if you take a camera
و لو أخذت كاميرا
and you point it at a random part of the sky,
و وجهتها نحو أي جزء من السماء عشوائياً،
and you just keep the shutter open,
و أبقيت عدسة الكاميرا مفتوحة،
as long as your camera is attached to the Hubble Space Telescope,
طالما أن كاميراتك متصلة مع تلسكوب هابل الفضائي،
it will see something like this.
سوف ترى شيئا من هذا القبيل.
Every one of these little blobs
كل واحدة من هذه البقع
is a galaxy roughly the size of our Milky Way --
عبارة عن مجرة بنفس حجم مجرتنا تقريبا--
a hundred billion stars in each of those blobs.
يوجد مائة بليون نجمة في كل بقعة منها.
There are approximately a hundred billion galaxies
يوجد ما يقارب مائة بليون مجرة
in the observable universe.
في الكون المرئي.
100 billion is the only number you need to know.
مائة بليون هو الرقم الوحيد الذي تحتاجون معرفته.
The age of the universe, between now and the Big Bang,
عمر الكون، بين هذه اللحظة والإنفجار الكبير،
is a hundred billion in dog years.
هو مائة بليون سنة قياساً بعمر الكلاب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Which tells you something about our place in the universe.
مما يخبركم شيئا عن وضعنا في هذا الكون.
One thing you can do with a picture like this is simply admire it.
هنالك شئ يمكن أن تفعله بصورة كهذه، هو ببساطة أن تعجب بها.
It's extremely beautiful.
إنها جميلة لأبعد الحدود.
I've often wondered, what is the evolutionary pressure
لطالما تساءلت ، ما هو الضغط التطوري
that made our ancestors in the Veldt adapt and evolve
الذي جعل أسلافنا في المروج يتأقلموا و يتطوروا
to really enjoy pictures of galaxies
ليصلوا إلى فكرة الإستمتاع الحقيقي بصور المجرات
when they didn't have any.
عندما لم يكن لديهم أي منها.
But we would also like to understand it.
و لكننا نريد أيضا أن نفهمها.
As a cosmologist, I want to ask, why is the universe like this?
كعالم كون، أريد أن أسأل ، لماذا الكون هكذا؟
One big clue we have is that the universe is changing with time.
عندنا دليل كبير واحد و هو أن الكون يتغير مع الزمن.
If you looked at one of these galaxies and measured its velocity,
إذا نظرتم إلى إحدى هذه المجرات و قمتم بقياس سرعتها،
it would be moving away from you.
سوف تجدون أنها تتحرك مبتعدة عنكم.
And if you look at a galaxy even farther away,
و لو نظرتم إلى مجرة أبعد،
it would be moving away faster.
سوف تجدون أنها تبتعد عنا أسرع.
So we say the universe is expanding.
لذلك نقول أن الكون يتمدد.
What that means, of course, is that, in the past,
ما يعنيه ذلك، بالتأكيد، هو أنه في الماضي،
things were closer together.
كانت الأشياء أقرب لبعضها.
In the past, the universe was more dense,
في الماضي، كان الكون أكبر كثافة،
and it was also hotter.
و كان أيضا أسخن.
If you squeeze things together, the temperature goes up.
إذا ضعطت الأشياء مع بعضها ، فإن درجة الحرارة ترتفع.
That kind of makes sense to us.
هذا الأمر منطقي بالنسبة لنا.
The thing that doesn't make sense to us as much
الأمر الغير منظقي بالنسبة لنا بنفس القدر
is that the universe, at early times, near the Big Bang,
هو أن الكون، في الأزمنة القديمة، قرب زمن الإنفجار الكبير،
was also very, very smooth.
كان أيضا متجانس، بصورة كبيرة جدا.
You might think that that's not a surprise.
قد تعتقد أن هذا الامر ليس بالمفاجأة.
The air in this room is very smooth.
الهواء في الغرفة متجانس للغاية.
You might say, "Well, maybe things just smoothed themselves out."
قد تقول،" حسن ، ربما الأمور تجانست من تلقاء نفسها"
But the conditions near the Big Bang are very, very different
لكن الأحوال قرب الإنفجار الكبير ، مختلفة للغاية ،
than the conditions of the air in this room.
من حال الهواء في هذه العرفة.
In particular, things were a lot denser.
بالتحديد الأشياء ، كانت كثافتها أكبر بكثير.
The gravitational pull of things
سحب الجاذبية للأشياء
was a lot stronger near the Big Bang.
كان أقوى بكثير قرب الإنفجار الكبير.
What you have to think about
ما يجب أن تفكر فيه
is we have a universe with a hundred billion galaxies,
هو أننا نملك كوناً بمائة بليون مجرة،
a hundred billion stars each.
بمائة بليون نجمة لكل مجرة.
At early times, those hundred billion galaxies
في الأزمنة السحيقة، المائة بليون مجرة هذه
were squeezed into a region about this big --
كانت مضغوطة في منطقة بهذا الحجم--
literally -- at early times.
حرفيا، في الأزمنة السحيقة.
And you have to imagine doing that squeezing
و لك أن تتخيل عمل هذا الضغط
without any imperfections,
بدون أي خلل،
without any little spots
بدون أي نقاط صغيرة
where there were a few more atoms than somewhere else.
تحتوي على عدد أكبر بقليل من الذرات، أكبر من عدد الذرات الموجودة في نقطة أخرى.
Because if there had been, they would have collapsed under the gravitational pull
لأنه لو كانت كذلك، كانت ستنهار تحت سحب الجاذبية
into a huge black hole.
داخل ثقب أسود كبير.
Keeping the universe very, very smooth at early times
الإحتفاظ بالكون في غاية التجانس في الأزمنة السحيقة
is not easy; it's a delicate arrangement.
ليس سهلا، إنه ترتيب دقيق.
It's a clue
إنه دليل
that the early universe is not chosen randomly.
على أن الكون البدائي لم يتم إختياره عشوائياً.
There is something that made it that way.
هنالك قوة جعلته بهذه الطريقة.
We would like to know what.
نريد أن نعرف ما هي هذه القوة.
So part of our understanding of this was given to us by Ludwig Boltzmann,
جزء من فهمنا لهذا ،تم إعطاؤه لنا من لدويج بولتزمان،
an Austrian physicist in the 19th century.
عالم فيزياء نمساوي في القرن التاسع عشر.
And Boltzmann's contribution was that he helped us understand entropy.
و مساهمة بولتزمان كانت أنه ساعدنا على فهم الإنتروبيا.
You've heard of entropy.
سمعتم عن الأنتروبيا.
It's the randomness, the disorder, the chaoticness of some systems.
إنها العشوائية، الإضطراب، الفوضوية في بعض الأنظمة.
Boltzmann gave us a formula --
لقد أعطانا بولتزمان معادلة--
engraved on his tombstone now --
محفورة على شاهد قبره اليوم--
that really quantifies what entropy is.
و التي حقا تساعد في قياس كمية الأنتروبيا.
And it's basically just saying
و هي جوهريا تقول
that entropy is the number of ways
أن الأنتروبيا هي عدد الطرق
we can rearrange the constituents of a system so that you don't notice,
التي يمكن بها إعادة ترتيب مكونات النظام من دون ملاحظة ذلك التغيير،
so that macroscopically it looks the same.
بحيث تبدو متشابهة بوضوح للعين.
If you have the air in this room,
إذا أخذنا الهواء في هذه الغرفة،
you don't notice each individual atom.
فأنت لا تلاحظ كل ذرة مستقلة.
A low entropy configuration
تكوين إنتروبيا منخفض
is one in which there's only a few arrangements that look that way.
يكون فيه فقط عدد قليل من الترتيبات التي تبدو بهذه الطريقة.
A high entropy arrangement
ترتيب إنتروبيا مرتفع
is one that there are many arrangements that look that way.
يوجد فيه عدد كبير من الترتييات التي تبدو بهذه الطريقة.
This is a crucially important insight
هذه هي نظرة في غاية الأهمية،
because it helps us explain
لأنها تساعدنا على تفسير
the second law of thermodynamics --
القانون الثاني للدينميكا الحرارية--
the law that says that entropy increases in the universe,
القانون الذي يقول أن الإنتروبيا في تزايد في الكون،
or in some isolated bit of the universe.
أو في جزء معزول من الكون.
The reason why entropy increases
السبب الذي يجعل الإنتروبيا تتزايد
is simply because there are many more ways
لأنه ببساطة توجد طرق كثيرة
to be high entropy than to be low entropy.
لتصبح إنتروبيا مرتفعة أكثر من أن تصبح أنتروبيا منخفضة.
That's a wonderful insight,
هذه نظرة رائعة،
but it leaves something out.
لكنها تستبعد شيئا.
This insight that entropy increases, by the way,
هذه الفكرة التي تقول أن الإنتروبيا تتزايد، بالمناسبة،
is what's behind what we call the arrow of time,
هي السبب وراء ما نسمية خط الزمن،
the difference between the past and the future.
الفرق بين الماضي والمستقبل.
Every difference that there is
كل فرق موجود
between the past and the future
بين الماضي والمستقبل
is because entropy is increasing --
هو بسبب تزايد الأنتروبيا--
the fact that you can remember the past, but not the future.
حقيقة أنك تستطيع تذكر الماضي، و لكن ليس المستقبل.
The fact that you are born, and then you live, and then you die,
حقيقة أنك تولد، ثم تعيش، ثم تموت،
always in that order,
دائما بهذا الترتيب،
that's because entropy is increasing.
هذا بسبب تزايد الإنتروبيا.
Boltzmann explained that if you start with low entropy,
بولتزمان شرح أنه إذا بدأت بإنتروبيا منخفضة،
it's very natural for it to increase
فإنه من الطبيعي أن تتزايد،
because there's more ways to be high entropy.
لأنه توجد طرق أكثر لتصبح إنتروبيا مرتفعة.
What he didn't explain
ما لم يشرحه
was why the entropy was ever low in the first place.
هو لماذا كانت الإنتروبيا منخفضة أصلاً في البدء.
The fact that the entropy of the universe was low
حقيقة أن إنتروبيا الكون كانت منخفضة
was a reflection of the fact
كانت إنعكاسا لحقيقة
that the early universe was very, very smooth.
أن الكون كان في غاية التجانس.
We'd like to understand that.
نحن نريد فهم ذلك.
That's our job as cosmologists.
هذا هو عملنا كعلماء كون.
Unfortunately, it's actually not a problem
للأسف الشديد ، إنها في الواقع مسألة
that we've been giving enough attention to.
لم نعطها الكثير من الإهتمام.
It's not one of the first things people would say,
إنها ليست من الأشياء الأولى التي سيقولها الناس،
if you asked a modern cosmologist,
إذا سألت عالم كون حديث،
"What are the problems we're trying to address?"
" ما هي المشاكل التي نحاول أن نعالجها؟"
One of the people who did understand that this was a problem
أحد الأشخاص الذين فهموا هذه مشكلة
was Richard Feynman.
كان ريتشارد فاينمان.
50 years ago, he gave a series of a bunch of different lectures.
من خمسين عاماً، أعطى سلسلة من المحاضرات المتنوعة.
He gave the popular lectures
أعطى تلك المحاضرات الشائعة
that became "The Character of Physical Law."
التي أصبحت تسمى: " طابع القانون الفيزيائي"
He gave lectures to Caltech undergrads
لقد أعطى محاضرات لطلبة كالتك الغير متخرجين
that became "The Feynman Lectures on Physics."
و أصبحت تسمى " محاضرات فاينمان في الفيزياء"
He gave lectures to Caltech graduate students
و أعطى محاضرات لطلبة كالتك المتخرجين
that became "The Feynman Lectures on Gravitation."
و أصبحت تسمى " محاضرات فاينمان في الجاذبية"
In every one of these books, every one of these sets of lectures,
في كل واحد من هذه الكتب ، و كل واحدة من هذه المحاضرات،
he emphasized this puzzle:
لقد ركز على هذا اللغز :
Why did the early universe have such a small entropy?
لماذا كان للكون إنتروبيا منخفضة بهذا الشكل ؟
So he says -- I'm not going to do the accent --
و يذهب ليقول--لن أقلد لهجته--
he says, "For some reason, the universe, at one time,
إنه يقول ،" لسبب ما ، الكون ، في لحظة ما،
had a very low entropy for its energy content,
كان له إنتروبيا منخفضة للغاية لمحتوى طاقته،
and since then the entropy has increased.
و منذ ذلك الوقت فإن الإنتروبيا في تزايد.
The arrow of time cannot be completely understood
خط الزمن لا يمكن فهمه بصورة كاملة
until the mystery of the beginnings of the history of the universe
حتي يتم فهم بدايات تاريخ الكون و غموضه
are reduced still further
بصورة أوضح و الإنتقال
from speculation to understanding."
من التخمينات إلى الفهم الحقيقي"
So that's our job.
و هذا هو عملنا.
We want to know -- this is 50 years ago, "Surely," you're thinking,
نحن نريد أن نعرف-- هذا منذ خمسين سنه،" أنتم بكل تأكيد تفكرون،
"we've figured it out by now."
أكيد لقد حللنا اللغز منذ ذلك الوقت."
It's not true that we've figured it out by now.
و هذا ليس حقيقيا أننا حللنا اللغز الآن.
The reason the problem has gotten worse,
السبب الذي جعل المسألة تسوء ،
rather than better,
بدلاً من أن تتحسن،
is because in 1998
أنه في عام 1998
we learned something crucial about the universe that we didn't know before.
تعلمنا شيئا مصيريا عن الكون لم نكن نعرفه من قبل.
We learned that it's accelerating.
لقد تعلمنا أنه يتسارع.
The universe is not only expanding.
الكون لا يتمدد فحسب.
If you look at the galaxy, it's moving away.
إذا نظرت إلى المجرة، فإنها تتحرك مبتعدة.
If you come back a billion years later and look at it again,
إذا عدت بعد بليون سنة و نظرت مرة أخرى،
it will be moving away faster.
سوف تكون مبتعدة بصورة أكبر.
Individual galaxies are speeding away from us faster and faster
كل مجرة تتسارع مبتعدة عنا أسرع و أسرع.
so we say the universe is accelerating.
فنحن نقول الكون يتسارع.
Unlike the low entropy of the early universe,
خلافاً للإنتروبيا المنخفضة للكون في الزمن الأول،
even though we don't know the answer for this,
و بالرغم من أننا لا نملك الإجابة لهذا،
we at least have a good theory that can explain it,
على الأقل فإننا نملك نظرية جيدة تستطيع تفسير ذلك،
if that theory is right,
إذا كانت هذه النظرية صحيحة،
and that's the theory of dark energy.
و هذه هي نظرية الطاقة المظلمة.
It's just the idea that empty space itself has energy.
إنها فكرة أن ذلك الفضاء الفارغ يمتلك في نفسه طاقة.
In every little cubic centimeter of space,
في كل سنتميتر مكعب من الفضاء،
whether or not there's stuff,
بغض النظر عن وجود شئ،
whether or not there's particles, matter, radiation or whatever,
بغض النظر عن وجود جسيمات، مادة،إشعاع ، أو أي شئ آخر،
there's still energy, even in the space itself.
فإنه توجد طاقة ، في الفضاء نفسه.
And this energy, according to Einstein,
و هذه الطاقة وفقاً لآينشتاين،
exerts a push on the universe.
تبذل دفعاً على الكون.
It is a perpetual impulse
إنه دفع أبدي
that pushes galaxies apart from each other.
قام بدفع المجرات بعيدا عن بعضها.
Because dark energy, unlike matter or radiation,
لأن الطاقة المظلمة، بخلاف المادة و الإشعاع،
does not dilute away as the universe expands.
لا تتخافت مع تمدد الكون.
The amount of energy in each cubic centimeter
كمية الطاقة في كل سنتميتر مكعب
remains the same,
تبقى نفسها،
even as the universe gets bigger and bigger.
حتى عندما يكبر الكون أكثر و أكثر.
This has crucial implications
هذا يترتب عليه آثار حاسمة
for what the universe is going to do in the future.
على ما سيفعله الكون في المستقبل.
For one thing, the universe will expand forever.
الشئ الأول ، أن الكون سوف يتمدد للأبد.
Back when I was your age,
عندما كنت في عمركم،
we didn't know what the universe was going to do.
لم نكن نعرف ما الذي سيفعله الكون.
Some people thought that the universe would recollapse in the future.
بعض الناس إعتقدوا أن الكون سوف يعود و ينهار في المستقبل.
Einstein was fond of this idea.
آينشتاين كان مولعاً بهذه الفكرة.
But if there's dark energy, and the dark energy does not go away,
لكن إذا كان هنالك طاقة مظلمة ، وهذه الطاقة المظلمة لا تتبدد،
the universe is just going to keep expanding forever and ever and ever.
فإن الكون سوف يظل يتمدد لأبد الآبدين.
14 billion years in the past,
أربعة عشر بليون سنة في الماضي،
100 billion dog years,
مائة بليون سنة بعمر الكلاب،
but an infinite number of years into the future.
و لكن برقم غير محدود من السنين في المستقبل.
Meanwhile, for all intents and purposes,
في هذه الأثناء، لمقاصدنا و أغراضنا،
space looks finite to us.
فإن الفضاء يبدو محدوداً بالنسبة لنا.
Space may be finite or infinite,
الفضاء قد يكون محدوداً أو غير محدود،
but because the universe is accelerating,
و لكن لأن الكون يتسارع،
there are parts of it we cannot see
هنالك أجزاء منه لا نستطيع رؤيتها
and never will see.
و لن نراها أبداً.
There's a finite region of space that we have access to,
توجد منطقة محدودة في الفضاء نستطيع الوصول إليها،
surrounded by a horizon.
محاطة بأفق.
So even though time goes on forever,
و بالرغم من أن الزمن مستمر للأبد،
space is limited to us.
الفضاء محدود بالنسبة لنا.
Finally, empty space has a temperature.
أخيرا، الفضاء الفارغ يمتلك درجة حرارة.
In the 1970s, Stephen Hawking told us
في سبعينات القرن الماضي ، أخبرنا ستيفن هوكنج
that a black hole, even though you think it's black,
أن الثقب الأسود، حتى لو بدا لنا أسوداً،
it actually emits radiation
فإنه في الحقيقة ينبعث منه إشعاع،
when you take into account quantum mechanics.
عندما تضع في إعتبارك ميكانيكا الكم.
The curvature of space-time around the black hole
فإن منحنى الفضاء-الزمن حول الثقب الأسود
brings to life the quantum mechanical fluctuation,
يحي تردد ميكانيكا الكم،
and the black hole radiates.
و الثقب الأسود يشع.
A precisely similar calculation by Hawking and Gary Gibbons
حسابات مماثلة من هوكنج و جاري جيبونز
showed that if you have dark energy in empty space,
أظهرت ، أنه لو كان لديك طاقة مظلمة في الفضاء الفارغ،
then the whole universe radiates.
فإن الكون كله يشع.
The energy of empty space
طاقة الفضاء الفارغ
brings to life quantum fluctuations.
تحي ترددات الكم.
And so even though the universe will last forever,
و لذلك و بالرغم من أن الكون سوف يدوم للأبد،
and ordinary matter and radiation will dilute away,
والمادة والإشعاع العاديين سوف يتخافتان بعيدا،
there will always be some radiation,
سوف يكون هنالك دائما بعض الإشعاع،
some thermal fluctuations,
بعض الترددات الحرارية،
even in empty space.
حتى في الفضاء الفارغ.
So what this means
فما يعنيه ذلك
is that the universe is like a box of gas
هو أن الكون كصندوق من الغاز
that lasts forever.
يدوم للأبد.
Well what is the implication of that?
فما هي إذن الآثار المترتبة على ذلك ؟
That implication was studied by Boltzmann back in the 19th century.
الآثار درست من قبل بولتزمان في القرن التاسع عشر.
He said, well, entropy increases
لقد قال، أن الأنتروبيا تتزايد
because there are many, many more ways
لأنه توجد طرق كثيرة أكثر بكثير
for the universe to be high entropy, rather than low entropy.
للكون ليصبح بأنتروبيا مرتفعة، من أن يصبح بأنتروبيا منخفضة.
But that's a probabilistic statement.
لكن هذه عبارة إحتمالية.
It will probably increase,
من المحتمل أن يتزايد،
and the probability is enormously huge.
و الإحتمال كبير للغاية.
It's not something you have to worry about --
هذا ليس شيئاً يجب أن تقلق بشأنه--
the air in this room all gathering over one part of the room and suffocating us.
تجمع الهواء في هذه الغرفة في جزء صغير منها ، مما سيؤدي لإختناقنا.
It's very, very unlikely.
إنه أمر غير محتمل على أكثر الفروض.
Except if they locked the doors
فيما عدا لو قاموا بغلق الأبواب
and kept us here literally forever,
و أبقونا هنا حرفيا للأبد،
that would happen.
فإن ذلك سيحدث.
Everything that is allowed,
كل ما هو مسموح به،
every configuration that is allowed to be obtained by the molecules in this room,
كل ترتيب مسموح به من الجزيئات الموجودة في هذه الغرفة،
would eventually be obtained.
يمكن الحصول عليها في النهاية.
So Boltzmann says, look, you could start with a universe
فبولتزمان يقول، أنظروا، يمكن أن تبدأ بكون
that was in thermal equilibrium.
بإتزان حراري.
He didn't know about the Big Bang. He didn't know about the expansion of the universe.
لم يكن يعرف عن الإنفجار الكبير . لم يكن يعلم عن تمدد الكون.
He thought that space and time were explained by Isaac Newton --
لقد ظن أن الفضاء والزمن تم شرحهم من قبل إسحق نيوتن--
they were absolute; they just stuck there forever.
و هما مطلقان ، و هما عالقان هنالك للأبد.
So his idea of a natural universe
لذا ففكرته عن كون طبيعي
was one in which the air molecules were just spread out evenly everywhere --
كانت جزيئات هوائية موزعة بالتساوي في كل مكان--
the everything molecules.
الجزيئات هي كل شئ.
But if you're Boltzmann, you know that if you wait long enough,
لكنك لو كنت بولتزمان، أنت تعرف، أنه لو انتظرت فترة كافية،
the random fluctuations of those molecules
الترددات العشوائية لهذه الجزيئات
will occasionally bring them
سوف ترتبهم من حين لآخر
into lower entropy configurations.
بصورة أنتروبيا منخفضة.
And then, of course, in the natural course of things,
و بعد ذلك ،بكل تأكيد،المسار الطبيعي للأشياء،
they will expand back.
سوف تتمدد مرة أخرى.
So it's not that entropy must always increase --
فالأمر ليس أن الأنتروبيا يجب أن تتزايد دائماً--
you can get fluctuations into lower entropy,
يمكن أن تحصل على ترددات في الإنتروبيا المنخفضة،
more organized situations.
حالات أكثر ترتيباً.
Well if that's true,
حسن، إذا كان ذلك صحيحاً،
Boltzmann then goes onto invent
بولتزمان يستمر في إبتكار
two very modern-sounding ideas --
فكرتين حين تسمعهما فهما يوحيان بالحداثة--
the multiverse and the anthropic principle.
الكون المتعدد و المبدأ الأنثروبي.
He says, the problem with thermal equilibrium
يقول ، أن المشكلة مع التوازن الحراري
is that we can't live there.
أننا لا نستطيع أن نعيش هنالك.
Remember, life itself depends on the arrow of time.
تذكروا، الحياة نفسها تعتمد على خط الزمن.
We would not be able to process information,
لم نكن لنقدر على معالجة المعلومات،
metabolize, walk and talk,
القيام بعمليات الإستقلاب، المشي و الكلام،
if we lived in thermal equilibrium.
لو كنا نعيش في توازن حراري.
So if you imagine a very, very big universe,
إذن لو تخيلتم ، كونا كبيرا للغاية،
an infinitely big universe,
كون بلا حدود،
with randomly bumping into each other particles,
بأجسام تتصادم مع بعضها عشوائياً،
there will occasionally be small fluctuations in the lower entropy states,
سوف يكون هنالك بين الحين و الآخر ترددات صغيرة في حالات الأنتروبيا المنخفضة،
and then they relax back.
ثم سوف تتمدد مرة أخرى.
But there will also be large fluctuations.
و لكن سيوجد أيضاً ترددات كبيرة.
Occasionally, you will make a planet
بين حين و آخر ، سوف يتكون كوكب
or a star or a galaxy
أو نجم أو مجرة
or a hundred billion galaxies.
أو حتى مئات البلايين من المجرات.
So Boltzmann says,
إذن فبولتزمان يقول،
we will only live in the part of the multiverse,
نحن فقط سنسكن في جزء الأكوان المتعددة،
in the part of this infinitely big set of fluctuating particles,
في الجزء الذي به هذه المجموعة الكبيرة من ترددات الأجسام الغير محدودة،
where life is possible.
حيث الحياة ممكنة.
That's the region where entropy is low.
هذه هي المنطقة التي فيها الأنتروبيا منخفضة.
Maybe our universe is just one of those things
ربما كان كوننا أحد هذه الأشياء
that happens from time to time.
التي تحدث من مرة إلى أخرى.
Now your homework assignment
و الآن واجبكم المنزلي
is to really think about this, to contemplate what it means.
هو أن تفكروا حقا في هذا ، و التأمل فيما يعنيه.
Carl Sagan once famously said
كارل ساجان قال قولته المشهورة
that "in order to make an apple pie,
"من أجل أن تصنع فطيرة تفاح،
you must first invent the universe."
يجب أن تخترع أولا الكون"
But he was not right.
لكنه لم يكن على صواب.
In Boltzmann's scenario, if you want to make an apple pie,
حسب سيناريو بولتزمان ، إذا كنت تريد عمل فطيرة تفاح،
you just wait for the random motion of atoms
تنتظر فقط الحركة العشوائية للذرات
to make you an apple pie.
لعمل فطيرة تفاح.
That will happen much more frequently
هذا سيحدث بتكرار أكبر
than the random motions of atoms
من الحركات العشوائية للذرات
making you an apple orchard
تكون لك بستان تفاح
and some sugar and an oven,
و بعض السكر و فرن،
and then making you an apple pie.
و بعد ذلك تكون لك فطيرة التفاح.
So this scenario makes predictions.
إذن هذا السيناريو يوفر تنبؤات.
And the predictions are
و هذه التنبؤات هي
that the fluctuations that make us are minimal.
أن الترددات التي تصنعنا هي في الحد الأدنى.
Even if you imagine that this room we are in now
حتى لو تخيلتم هذه الغرفة التي نحن فيها الآن
exists and is real and here we are,
موجودة و حقيقية و ها نحن ذا ،
and we have, not only our memories,
و لا نملك ذاكرتنا فقط ،
but our impression that outside there's something
و لكن إنطباعاتنا أن في الخارج يوجد شئ ما
called Caltech and the United States and the Milky Way Galaxy,
يدعى كالتك و الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية و مجرة درب التبانة ،
it's much easier for all those impressions to randomly fluctuate into your brain
إنه من الأسهل أن تتردد كل هذه الإنطباعات عشوائيا في أذهاننا
than for them actually to randomly fluctuate
من أن تتردد واقعياً
into Caltech, the United States and the galaxy.
لتصبح كالتك ، الولايات المتحدة و المجرة.
The good news is that,
الخبر السار هو
therefore, this scenario does not work; it is not right.
أن هذا السيناريو لا يعمل ، إنه غير صحيح.
This scenario predicts that we should be a minimal fluctuation.
هذا السيناريو يتنبأ أننا يجب أن نكون تردداً أدنى.
Even if you left our galaxy out,
حتى لو استبعدتم مجرتنا ،
you would not get a hundred billion other galaxies.
لن تحصلوا على مائة بليون مجرة أخرى.
And Feynman also understood this.
و فاينمان فهم ذلك أيضاً.
Feynman says, "From the hypothesis that the world is a fluctuation,
فاينمان يقول ،" من فرضية أن العالم هو تردد،
all the predictions are that
كل التنبؤات هي،
if we look at a part of the world we've never seen before,
أننا لو نظرنا إلى جزء من الكون لم نره من قبل،
we will find it mixed up, and not like the piece we've just looked at --
نجده مضطرب ، و ليس كالجزء الذي نظرنا إليه في--
high entropy.
حالة إنتروبيا مرتفعة.
If our order were due to a fluctuation,
لو كان نظامنا ناتجاً عن تردد ،
we would not expect order anywhere but where we have just noticed it.
لن نتوقع النظام في أي مكان سوي في المكان الذي لاحظناه.
We therefore conclude the universe is not a fluctuation."
لذلك نستنتج أن الكون ليس تردداً"
So that's good. The question is then what is the right answer?
حسن ذلك جيد. السؤال هو ما هي إذن الإجابة الصحيحة ؟
If the universe is not a fluctuation,
إذا كان الكون ليس تردداً،
why did the early universe have a low entropy?
لماذا كان للكون إنتروبيا منخفضة ؟
And I would love to tell you the answer, but I'm running out of time.
و أرغب كثيراً أن أخبركم الإجابة ، لكن الزمن بدأ يداهمني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here is the universe that we tell you about,
ها هو الكون الذي نخبركم عنه ،
versus the universe that really exists.
في مقابل الكون الحقيقي الموجود.
I just showed you this picture.
لقد عرضت لكم هذه الصورة للتو.
The universe is expanding for the last 10 billion years or so.
الكون يتمدد منذ العشر بلايين سنة الماضية.
It's cooling off.
و هو يبرد.
But we now know enough about the future of the universe
و كلنا الآن نعرف ما فيه الكفاية عن مستقبل الكون
to say a lot more.
لقول أكثر من ذلك.
If the dark energy remains around,
إذا استمرت الطاقة المظلمة في التواجد،
the stars around us will use up their nuclear fuel, they will stop burning.
النجوم من حولنا سوف تستخدم كل طاقتها النووية ، و سوف تتوقف عن الإحتراق.
They will fall into black holes.
سوف تتهاوي في الثقوب السوداء.
We will live in a universe
سوف نعيش في كون
with nothing in it but black holes.
لا شئ فيه سوى الثقوب السوداء.
That universe will last 10 to the 100 years --
هذا الكون سوف يعيش عشرة أس مائة سنة --
a lot longer than our little universe has lived.
أطول بكثير مما عاشه كوننا الصغير.
The future is much longer than the past.
المستقبل أطول بكثير من الماضي.
But even black holes don't last forever.
لكن حتى الثقوب السوداء لا تستمر للأبد.
They will evaporate,
سوف تتبخر،
and we will be left with nothing but empty space.
و سوف لن يبقى لنا سوى الفضاء الفارغ.
That empty space lasts essentially forever.
هذا الفضاء الفارغ سوف يدوم للأبد.
However, you notice, since empty space gives off radiation,
و لكن ، تلاحظون ، بما أن الفضاء الفارغ ينتج إشعاع ،
there's actually thermal fluctuations,
فإنه توجد ترددات حرارية ،
and it cycles around
و تدور
all the different possible combinations
حول كل الترتيبات الممكنة
of the degrees of freedom that exist in empty space.
لدرجات الحرية الموجودة في الفضاء الفارغ.
So even though the universe lasts forever,
فإذن و بالرغم من أن الكون يدوم للأبد ،
there's only a finite number of things
يوجد عدد محدود من الأشياء
that can possibly happen in the universe.
التي من الممكن أن تحدث في الكون.
They all happen over a period of time
و كلها تحدث في فترة من الزمن
equal to 10 to the 10 to the 120 years.
تساوي عشرة أس عشرة أس مائة و عشرون عاماً.
So here's two questions for you.
أوجه سؤالين لكم.
Number one: If the universe lasts for 10 to the 10 to the 120 years,
السؤال الأول :إذا كان الكون يمتد لعشرة أس عشرة أس مائة و عشرون عاماً،
why are we born
لماذا نولد
in the first 14 billion years of it,
في السنوات الأربعة عشر بليون الأولى منها،
in the warm, comfortable afterglow of the Big Bang?
في الشفق المريح الدافئ للإنفجار الكبير ؟
Why aren't we in empty space?
لماذ نحن لسنا في الفضاء الفارغ ؟
You might say, "Well there's nothing there to be living,"
قد تقولون ، " لأنه لا يوجد شئ حي هنالك "
but that's not right.
لكن هذا ليس صحيحاً.
You could be a random fluctuation out of the nothingness.
يمكن أن تكونوا تردداً عشوائياً من لا شئ.
Why aren't you?
لماذا لستم كذلك؟
More homework assignment for you.
المزيد من الواجبات المنزلية لكم.
So like I said, I don't actually know the answer.
إذن كما قلت ، فإني لا أملك حقيقة الإجابة.
I'm going to give you my favorite scenario.
سوف أعطيكم السيناريو المفضل بالنسبة لي.
Either it's just like that. There is no explanation.
إما أن الأمر هكذا. لا يوجد تفسير.
This is a brute fact about the universe
هذه حقيقة قاسية عن الكون.
that you should learn to accept and stop asking questions.
عليك أن تقبل بها و تتوقف عن الأسئلة.
Or maybe the Big Bang
أو ربما الإنفجار الكبير
is not the beginning of the universe.
ليس بداية الكون.
An egg, an unbroken egg, is a low entropy configuration,
البيضة ،بيضة غير مكسورة، هو تكوين منخفض الأنتروبيا،
and yet, when we open our refrigerator,
و مع ذلك ، عندما نفتح باب الثلاجة،
we do not go, "Hah, how surprising to find
لا تقول ،" هاه، يا للمفاجأة وجدت
this low entropy configuration in our refrigerator."
تكوينا منخفض الأنتروبيا في ثلاجتنا"
That's because an egg is not a closed system;
هذا لأن البيضة ليست منظومة مغلقة ؛
it comes out of a chicken.
إنها تأتي من الدجاجة.
Maybe the universe comes out of a universal chicken.
ربما الكون يأتي من دجاجة كونية.
Maybe there is something that naturally,
ربما يوجد شيئاً طبيعياً
through the growth of the laws of physics,
عبر نمو قوانين الفيزياء،
gives rise to universe like ours
ينتج عنه كوناً مثل كوننا
in low entropy configurations.
في تكوين إنتروبيا منخفضة.
If that's true, it would happen more than once;
إذا كان ذلك صحيحاً فسوف يحدث أكثر من مرة؛
we would be part of a much bigger multiverse.
سوف نكون جزءاً من أكوان متعددة أكبر بكثير.
That's my favorite scenario.
هذا هو السيناريو المفضل بالنسبة لي.
So the organizers asked me to end with a bold speculation.
المنظمون طلبوا مني أن أنهي بتوقع جرئ.
My bold speculation
توقعي الجرئ
is that I will be absolutely vindicated by history.
هو أنني سوف أجد تبريري تماما -من قبل التاريخ.
And 50 years from now,
و خمسون سنة من الآن،
all of my current wild ideas will be accepted as truths
كل أفكاري المجنونة سوف يتم قبولها كحقائق
by the scientific and external communities.
من المجتمعين العلمي و الخارجي.
We will all believe that our little universe
سوف نؤمن جميعنا أن كوننا الصغير
is just a small part of a much larger multiverse.
هو فقط جزء صغير من أكوان متعددة أكبر.
And even better, we will understand what happened at the Big Bang
و الأفضل من ذلك ، سوف نفهم ما حدث في الإنفجار الكبير
in terms of a theory
كنظرية
that we will be able to compare to observations.
يمكن مقارنتها مع الملاحظات.
This is a prediction. I might be wrong.
هذا تنبؤ.قد أكون مخطئاً.
But we've been thinking as a human race
و لكننا ظللنا نفكر كبشرية
about what the universe was like,
عن كيف هو الكون،
why it came to be in the way it did for many, many years.
و كيف أصبح على ما هو عليه ، لسنوات طويلة جداً.
It's exciting to think we may finally know the answer someday.
إنه من المثير أن نفكر أننا ربما نتوصل أخيراً إلى الإجابة في يوم ما.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)